A Guide to the Moon family records, 1806-1849
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Moon family records, 1806-1849
The Library of Virginia
43719
1.25 cu. ft. [5 boxes]
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection came to the Library of Virginia in three accessions.
Ledger, 1806-1809, lent for copying by Roy A. Moon, June 1978. (Accession 30001)
Account book, 1814-1815, lent for copying by Roy A. Moon, June 1978. (Accession 30049)
Original records, 1806-1849, gift of Roy A. Moon, April 2008. (Accession 43719) THIS ACCESSION IS USED TO IDENTIFY AND DESCRIBE THE ENTIRE COLLECTION.
Biographical Information
The Moon family resided in Campbell and Charlotte County, Virginia. Archelaus (Archibald) Moon married Martha Morton 11 February 1778 and died in Fayette County, Kentucky. They had three children: Josiah Pleasant, Martha, and Archibald. Martha Morton's cousin was William Archer Durrum of Appomattox County, Virginia.
Josiah Pleasant Moon was born in Charlotte County, Virginia, and married Elizabeth McKinney 18 September 1806. He died in Spout Spring, Virginia. They had nine children: Martha Morton (b. 1806), Susannah (b. 1809), Archalous (b. 1810), Charles (b, 1811), William (b. 1813), Thomas P. (b. 1814), Elizabeth Virginia (b. 1817), George Friend (b. 1820), and Mary Agnes (b. 1821). Josiah ran a merchants store in Campbell County, Virginia, with Robert Price and Thomas Palmer. Moon and Price also had a blacksmith shop next to the store. Moon also served as a revenue collector for the 11th Collection District of Virginia. His nephew, Charles McKinney served as a deputy collector.
Archalous Moon had a son, William Archer Moon, who had a farm in Campbell County, Virginia. Roy A. Moon, the son of William Archer Moon, was born 11 May 1923 in Spout Spring, Virginia. He attended VCU School of Pharmacy and was a pharmacist in Appomattox, Lynchburg, and Roanoke.
Scope and Content
Records, 1806-1849, of the Moon family including daybooks, ledgers, obituary, correspondence, and a will. Includes a daybook and ledger, 1806-1809, of a general store run by Josiah P. Moon, Robert Price, and Thomas Palmer in Campbell County, Virginia. Also includes the ledgers, 1827-1832, of a general store run by Bryan Akers, who probably took over the Moon store. Information found includes date of transaction, merchandise sold, quantity of merchandise purchased, form of payment, and amounts owed and paid. Merchandise sold includes dry goods, whiskey and liquors, hardware, hemp, clothing, spices, cookware, glass, gunpowder, and tobacco (often showing the warehouse to which shipped). The ledger is indexed.
Included are account books, 1814-1815, kept by Josiah P. Moon as revenue collector for the 11th Collection District of Virginia. The fees collected ledger lists duties paid and fines collected on a quarterly basis. Includes duties on licenses for stills, retailers' licenses, sales at auction, stamped papers received and sold; accounts of fines relative to stills and boilers, to retailers' licenses, and stamped papers; and accounts for measuring stills and boilers and for remission of fines. Includes date of license, to whom granted, place of distilling, and capacity of stills in Campbell, Charlotte, Halifax, and Pittsylvania Counties and Lynchburg. The expenses paid ledger includes accounts of cash received and paid out. Includes compensation and commissions paid to Moon, as well as monies collected. Also includes numbers of licenses sold for stills and boilers. The ledger was later used by William Archer Moon, farmer in Campbell County. Includes notes on breeding of cows and horses, sale of hogs, yellow den corn seed and boxwood branches sold, and address of relatives.
Miscellaneous papers include a typed transcript of the will of Josiah P. Moon, 1832, and an obituary of William Archer Durrum (undated). Also included is a letter, 12 May 1849, from Charles McKinney, Allensville, Kentucky, to Matthew Jouet McKinney, Appomattox County, Virginia. Topics include the Kentucky Convention of 1850 and issues regarding emancipation. Other topics include family, health, cholera in Tennessee, and on choosing a wife. (This is the original of LVA Acc. 30046)
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Josiah P. Moon, Robert Price, and Thomas Palmer store daybook, 1806-1809. (Box 1)
  Also available on Misc. reel 631.
- Josiah P. Moon, Robert Price, and Thomas Palmer store ledger, 1806-1809. (Box 2)
- Josiah P. Moon, Robert Price, and Thomas Palmer shop book ledger, 1806-1809. (Box 2)
- Josiah P. Moon tax ledgers, fees collected, 1814. (Box 3)
  Also available on Misc. reel 631
- Josiah P. Moon tax ledgers, expenses paid, 1814. (Box 3)
  Also includes farming notes of William Archer Moon, 1931-1932.
- Bryan Akers ledgers, 1827-1829. (Box 4)
- Bryan Akers ledgers, 1829-1831. (Box 4)
- Bryan Akers ledgers, 1831-1832. (Box 5)
- Josiah P. Moon will, 1832. (Box 5)
  Transcript copy
- Charles McKinney letter, 12 May 1849. (Box 5)
  To Matthew Jouet McKinney, Appomattox County, Virginia
- Obituary of William Archer Durrum, nd. (Box 5)